Guide to the James Grabow Photographs and Family Papers 1876, 1902-2007 PR 317
New-York Historical Society
James D. Grabow photographs and family papers
1876, 1902-2007
New-York Historical Society
Grabow, James D.
PR 317
3.67 Linear feet in two boxes and one oversize folder
This collection consists primarily of color snapshots and a smaller number of black and white photographic prints of cultural and historical sites in New York City and upstate New York taken between 1969 and 2000s by James Grabow. Highlights include images of the Staten Island Ferry and the "Mothball Fleet" of decommissioned Navy vessels on the Hudson River. There are also a few earlier snapshots and documents related to the Liebich family of Brooklyn, which Grabow's father married into.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection primarily contains photographs of historic and cultural sites in New York City and upstate New York taken by professional photographer James D. Grabow. The majority of the images are color snapshots taken between 1969 and 2000s. There are also a smaller number of black and white photographic prints, a few of which date back to the 1960s and 1930s, the latter taken by Grabow's father. Highlights include images of the Staten Island Ferry and the "Mothball Fleet" (i.e., decommissioned Navy vessels) on the Hudson River.
The collection also holds a small number of financial receipts, certificates, and ephemera dating mostly from the early twentieth century. These relate to the Liebich family of Brooklyn, which Grabow's father married into.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of James D. Grabow, 2015-2021
Related Materials
A collection of James Grabow's photographs that center on Maryland and Washington, DC, are held by the Maryland Historical Society, call number PP304.
Historic buildings -- New York (State) -- Photographs.; Historic sites -- New York (State) -- Photographs.; Museums -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Public institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Black-and-white photographs.; Certificates.; Color photographs.; Photographs.; Brooklyn Sunday School Union -- Hymnals.; Food Sales Company Club -- Photographs.
- Series I: Color snapshots, 1969-2007; .42 Linear feet in a small box
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes 6x4 inch color snapshots taken by James Grabow in New York City and New York State. The specific subjects are noted in the container list.
  - Metropolitan Museum, 1989, 1993 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Metropolitan Museum, 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cloisters Museum (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Guggenheim Museum, 1993 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Whitney Museum (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brooklyn Museum (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Midtown Manhattan, Christmas, 1970s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - World Trade Center (Photographs of and from) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Circle Line Cruise, circa 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Phillipse Mill and Manor House, Yonkers, NY, 2005, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kykuit, Sleepy Hollow, NY, 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lyndhurst, Tarrytown, NY, 2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sunnyside, Tarrytown, NY, 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Vanderbilt Mansion, Hyde Park, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Home of Franklin D. Roosevelt, Hyde Park, NY, 2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Val-Kill Cottage, Hyde Park, NY, 2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sagamore Hills, Oyster Bay, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Montgomery Place, Red Hook, NY, 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Van Cortlandt Manor, Croton-On-Hudson, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clermont (Livingston Family Estate), Germantown, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Locust Grove (home of Samuel B. Morse), Poughkeepsie, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Olana (Frederick Church House), Hudson, NY, 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Mills Mansion, Staatsburg, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
  - Wilderstein, Rhinebeck, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
  - Grant's Cottage, Wilton, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
  - George Eastman House, Rochester, NY, 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
  - Corning Glass Museum, Corning, NY, 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gillinder Glass Factory, Port Jervis, NY, 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
  - Old Stone Church Museum, Schoharie, NY, 2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
  - Glenn Curtiss Museum, Hammondsport, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
  - Northeast Car Museum, Norwich, NY, 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
  - War Plane Museum at Elmira-Corning Airport, circa 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
  - Lighthouse along Hudson River (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
  - West Point, 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fort Delaware, Narrowsburg, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fort McHenry, Lake George, NY, 2007 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fort Ticonderoga, 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 37)
  - Watervliet Armory, 2007 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 38)
  - Bennington Battlefield, Walloomsac, NY, 2004 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 39)
  - Stony Point Battlefield, 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 40)
  - Roebling's Canal Bridge, Minisink Ford, NY, 2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 41)
  - Howe Caverns, near Cobbleskill, NY, 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 42)
  - Views (12 slides) from top of World Trade Center, [1995] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
    Date not on slides, but referred to by donor in his transmittal letter.
  - Rockefeller Center at Christmas (5 slides); Bear Mountain Bridge (1); Stony Point State Park (4); repair barge for mothballed fleet (1), 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
- Series II: Black and white (gelatin silver) photographic prints, 1927-1995; 1.25 Linear feet in one flat box and one small folder
  The series holds several photographs of New York City and New York State, mostly taken by James Grabow. A few from the 1920s-30s were taken by D.W. Grabow, James's father. One of these photographs is of Louise Liebich, who would become James's mother. Although the bulk are black and white prints, twelve images are color slides taken by James Grabow of views from the top of the World Trade Center in 1995. Specific topics are listed in the container list.
  - Small Snapshots, 1932-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 43)
    Two photos of Louise Liebich at the statue in front of the Brooklyn Museum (identical photos but variously dated; likely 1932); a group of women parading in E. Williston Park, L.I. (4 July 1933); the steamships Normandie and RMS Queen Mary docked on the North (Hudson) River (June 1936); Boy Scouts on bus at the 42nd Street ferry (June 1937 June); Route 97 above Port Jervis, NY (1970); South Street seaport area (1970).
  - Staten Island Ferry, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Boats entering Hudson River from East River, Governor's Island in Background, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Niagara Falls, 1971 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cloisters Museum (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Empire State Building and Rockefeller Center, 1970s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Battery Park: War Memorial, View of Goethals Bridge and Statue of Liberty, 1970s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Tire Repair Storefront, 613 Washington Avenue, Brooklyn, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    Note
    Store was originally owned by photographer's grandfather
  - Mothballed Fleet, Hudson River, circa 1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    Separated Materials Note
    An oversize photographic print of the Mothball Fleet is housed in the Maritime History Collection, PR 100, FF28.
  - Stony Point Lighthouse, Montauk Point Lighthouse, Old Hook Windmill (East Hampton), 1970s-1980s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Snow photos with abandoned cars (one melted in gas station fire), 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Upstate snow photos, 1969, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- Series III. Family papers, 1876-1935; 2 Linear feet in 3 folders, including one oversize
  The series holds a small number of documents related to the Liebich family, especially Adelaide (the donor's aunt on his mother, Louise's, side and George, Adelaide and Louise's father). The specific documents are noted in the container list.
  - Family Papers, 1902-1930s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    The file holds a receipted property tax bill for 613 Washington Ave, Brooklyn (1902); several receipts for mortgage payments by George Liebich on the 613 Washington property (1904-1913); a Certificate of Proficiency in Typewriting to Adelaide Liebich from Girls' Com'l High School (1922); harmonica marketing material from M. Hohner, Inc (1930s?); and a packet of Niagara Falls souvenir postcards (1934).
  - Brooklyn Sunday School Union, 1876 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    One booklet: Hymns & Music for the school's 47th anniversary on 24 May 1876, with tie-in to the centennial celebration of the U.S.
  - Oversize Documents, 1904-1935 (Folder Flat File)
    3 certificates: marriage of Gerhard Heinrich Liebich to Rebecca Katharine Vogt, both of Brooklyn (1904), baptism of Adelaide Katharine Liebich (1904), and confirmation of Adelaide Liebich at St. Luke's Evangelical Lutheran Church (1920). Group photograph of the First Get Together of the Food Sales Company Club, Hotel Park Central (4 December 1935).